<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A brief discourse concerning the unlawfulness of the common-prayer-worship and of laying the hand on and kissing the booke in swearing / by a reverend and learned divine.</title>
            <author>Mather, Increase, 1639-1723.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 56KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50188</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">27565582</idno>
  <idno type="VID">110137</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240903098</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1186</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R43432</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">27565582</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50188)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 110137)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1728:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A brief discourse concerning the unlawfulness of the common-prayer-worship and of laying the hand on and kissing the booke in swearing / by a reverend and learned divine.</title>
                  <author>Mather, Increase, 1639-1723.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second impression.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[4], 43 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Reprinted at London,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>in the year 1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"The authorship is acknowledged by Increase Mather in Some remarks, on a pretended answer to a discourse concerning the common-prayer worship."--NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="corporate_name">Church of England. --  Book of common prayer.</term>
               <term type="corporate_name">Church of England --  Liturgy --  History.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Oaths.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:110137:1"/>
            <p> A Brief DISCOURSE Concerning the UNLAWFULNESS of the Common-Prayer-WORSHIP; AND OF Laying the HAND on AND Kissing the BOOK IN SVVEARING.</p>
            <p>By a Reverend and Learned Divine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Second Impression.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>2 Kings 18. 4.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>He removed the high places, and brake the Images, and cut down the Groves, and brake in pieces the brasen Serpent that</hi> Moses <hi>had made; for unto those dayes the Children of</hi> Israel <hi>did burn In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cense to it; and he called it</hi> Nehushtan.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Reprinted at <hi>London</hi> in the Year 1689.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:110137:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:110137:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THE following Discourse falling in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my hands, my Affection to the labouring Truths therein argued for, and my concernedness for the Information of them, that I am every way bound to be a Well-wisher to, quickly made me sensible, that to keep it in a private hand would be a more culpable Conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a Treasure, than to bury Gold; especially since the Golden mouth'd Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent hath long since convinced, that <hi>to conceal the Truth is to betray it.</hi> That this Lamp of the Sanctuary then may give Light unto the whole House, the Press hath been imployed to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate it; blessed be GOD for the
<pb facs="tcp:110137:3"/> Advantage which the Church now En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joys above former Ages, in so diffusive an Instrument of all Knowledge and Goodness, as that of Printing is become. I shall forbear to declare unto the World the Name of that worthy Person unto whom we are beholden for this Elaborate Composure, only that it hath for its Author a Learned and Pious Minister: I should be loth to occasion him any trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; and shall entreat the Reverend Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor to pardon my not asking his Consent in thus disposing of his Manuscript, and I am sure he will not be offended with me, when he shall hear that many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds have been thereby Established in <hi>the present Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:110137:3"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>MUltiplicity of Occasions and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versions will not permit me to return an Elaborate Answer to every one that shall send Questions to me. But as for your self, I have peculiar Cause to respect, and endeavour your Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. And inasmuch as the Enquiries which you have Communicated to me, are both Weighty and Seasonable, I have thought it <hi>Operae pretium,</hi> to spend some hours in Searching into the Controvert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Subjects, being also ready (as in Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty I am bound) to give a Reason of my Perswasion to such as shall in Seriousness demand it of me.</p>
            <p>Your first Question is thus Proposed,</p>
            <div n="1" type="question">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:110137:4"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVhat are the Reasons why you Judge it Ʋnlawfull to be present at, or to partake in the Common-Prayer-VVorship.</hi>
               </p>
               <div n="1" type="reason">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Answ.</hi> My First Reason is, <hi>From the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal of the Common-Prayer Book, which with the Ceremonies and Worship prescribed therein, I find to be in a great measure Popish and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenish.</hi> Some have causelesly Complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of Non-conformists, because they affirm that the <hi>English</hi> Liturgy is taken out of the Pope's <hi>Mass-book.</hi> It's true, that as the <hi>Mass-book</hi> is taken in a more strict fence, a great part of the <hi>English Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy</hi> is not to be found therein: But as the <hi>Missal</hi> is put for the whole <hi>Roman Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy,</hi> (and so it many times is, a part be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing put for the whole) it cannot be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed but that the Common-Prayer Book is from thence derived: There are things (as Prayers for the Dead, <hi>&amp;c.)</hi> in the <hi>Roman Liturgy</hi> which are not Translated into <hi>English,</hi> but very little is in the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish</hi> which is not to be found in the other. This is particularly cleared up by the Learned Author of the Book called <hi>Altare</hi>
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:110137:4"/>
                     <hi>Damascenum,</hi> which goeth under the Name of <hi>Didoclavius,</hi> but Mr. <hi>David Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derwood</hi> was the true Author. Also there are many Treatises in <hi>English</hi> which may be Consulted concerning this matter, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly, a Book called <hi>A Parallel between the Mass-book and the Liturgy, and the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomy of the Service Book,</hi> which goeth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Name of <hi>Dwalphintramis:</hi> And Mr. <hi>John Allin</hi> of <hi>Dedham</hi> in <hi>New-Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> his Defence of the Nine Positions, <hi>p.</hi> 63, 66. and a <hi>Discourse of Liturgies,</hi> by <hi>H. D.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If you would have a distinct Account of the Original of the Common Prayer Book, you must know, it was Collected out of three Superstitious Books: The first part of Publick Prayer is borrowed from the Papist's <hi>Breviary;</hi> that about Sacraments, Matrimony, Burials, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is taken out of the <hi>Ritual;</hi> the Order of Consecration, Epistles, Collects, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is gathered out of the <hi>Roman Missal.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Hence the <hi>English Liturgy</hi> has been well approved of by Papists. A Jesuit being asked how he liked the Service at <hi>Paul</hi>'s, gave this Answer, <hi>I have nothing against it, but that it is done by your Priests.</hi> When Secretary <hi>Walsingham</hi> had in Policy caus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:110137:5"/> two Popish Intelligencers then in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to have a View of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terbury-</hi>Service, they were Marvellously taken therewith, saying, <q rend="margQuotes">That the Pope had been misinformed, for their Service was very like his own:</q> And they there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon Endeavoured that the Pope's Bull might be recalled. Pope <hi>Pius</hi> the Fifth was willing to ratifie the Common Prayer Book by his Authority, if Queen <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi> would have so retained it. Dr. <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riar</hi> (a Popish Bigot) speaketh very fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourably of the <hi>English Liturgy,</hi> because he saith, <q rend="margQuotes">There is nothing in it Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presly contrary to theirs.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is very Strange that any of our Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgical Men should have the face to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny these things; but some of them have Ingenuously acknowledged the Truth of what we assert. He that has Written Mr. <hi>George Herbert</hi>'s Life, declares that he dislikes not the <hi>English Liturgy</hi> the more for being taken out of the <hi>Mass-book, It is</hi> (saith he) <hi>taken out as Gold from Dross: The wise Reformers knew</hi> Rome <hi>would cry Schism, Schism, and therefore they kept all they lawfully could keep, being loth to give offence;</hi> thus he. To this Objection, <hi>That the Form of our Liturgy is taken from An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichrist,</hi>
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:110137:5"/> Dr. <hi>Covel</hi>'s Answer is, <hi>We are sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry that their Weakness takes Offence at that which we hold as a Virtue in the Church of</hi> England; <hi>Namely, that we have so spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringly, and as it were unwillingly dissented from the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>for surely by An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichrist they mean her,</hi> Exam. <hi>p.</hi> 185. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise Dr. <hi>Boice</hi> and Mr. <hi>Wommock,</hi> who have Written in defence of the Common Prayer-Book, Confess that 'tis a Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Roman Catholick; but they say, Why should the Child be beaten for the Parents sake; to whom it has been well replyed, Why should not <hi>Hagar</hi> and <hi>Ishmael</hi> be both put out of Doors toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. A great Episcopalian owns that the <hi>Roman Liturgy</hi> is like a Leprous House, only he supposeth that the Compilers of the Common Prayer Book have <hi>picked, and scraped, and plaistered the House;</hi> but he should have considered that the Rub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bish of the Leprous House ought to be cast into an Unclean Place, and that the Leprosie breaks out still, therefore we may have no Communion with it: But enough of these Allegories. I shall fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther confirm this Argument by two Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Testimonies. The one is that of King <hi>Edward</hi> 6. who when the Popish Rebels
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:110137:6"/> in <hi>Devonshire</hi> took up Arms against the King, because of his establishing the <hi>English</hi> Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy, he wrote thus to them: <hi>It seemeth unto you a New Service, but it is indeed no other but the Old; the self-same words in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish, which were in Latin, saving a few things taken out, wich were so fond, that it had been a shame for to have them in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish. If the Service of the Church was good in Latin, it remains good in English; for nothing is altered, but to speak with Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge what was spoken with Ignorance, and to let you understand what is said for you.</hi> See Mr. <hi>Fox</hi> Acts and Monuments. <hi>Vol.</hi> 2. p. 669.</p>
                  <p>Another Testimony is that of King <hi>James</hi> of Famous Memory, who in his Speech to a National Assembly, <hi>Anno</hi> 1590 praiseth GOD that he was <hi>King in the Sincerest Church in the World; sincerer than the Church of</hi> England, <hi>for their Service is an</hi> Ill said Mass, <hi>sincerer than</hi> Geneva <hi>it self, for they observe</hi> Pasche and Yule. <hi>i. e. Easter and Christmass, and what Warrant have they for that?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But what need of words? Let such as have any Haesitancy about this matter, compare the <hi>Popish Missal,</hi> &amp;c. with the <hi>English Liturgy,</hi> and they will be convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced:
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:110137:6"/> For my own part I have done it, and am satisfied; now it is a known Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>im, <hi>Omnis honor Idoli est Idololatria.</hi> He that shall put any respect upon an Idol, cannot be clear from the Sin of Idolatry. But the Mass-Book is an Idol, and he that useth a Prayer, or joyns with a Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er taken out of that Book, thereby puts Honour upon an Idol. We ought not to name an Idol but with Detestation, much less may we offer it as worship to God, <hi>Psal.</hi> 16. 4. <hi>Exod.</hi> 23. 13. <hi>Hosea</hi> 2. 16, 17.</p>
                  <p>How then can we joyn in Prayers ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out of the Idolatrous Mass-Book, and offer them to the Holy GOD?</p>
                  <p>The Bishop of <hi>Exeter</hi> is too Lavish and Gaudy in his Rhetorick, when he tells us, That if <hi>Saint Paul were alive, he would use the English Liturgy;</hi> it was <hi>Pauls</hi> Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that Meat once offered to Idols should not be made use of, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 28. <hi>Ergo,</hi> a Service-Book offered to Idols ought not to be used, for there is a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Reason. We may here take Old <hi>Cyprian</hi>'s complaint, and say, <hi>Ad hoc ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum devoluta est Ecclesia ut id faciunt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stiani, quod Antichristiani faciunt.</hi> It must be acknowledged that the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:110137:7"/>
                     <hi>men</hi> as keep to the Thirty nine Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles in matters of Doctrine, are as Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox as any Protestants in the World, but as to Worship and Discipline they are extreamly Popish: Which has occasioned <hi>Gretzer (de Fest. Lib.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 2.) to give them the strange Name of <hi>Calvino-Papistae:</hi> The use of such a Liturgy doth harden the Papists in their Idolatry; yea, and the <hi>Jews</hi> themselves are scandalized there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by: It's a celebrated saying among them, <hi>That Christians have their Tephilloth from Armillus.</hi> h. e. Their Prayer-Books from Antichrist. Moreover, that the <hi>English</hi> Liturgy is originally Heathenish as well as Popish, is manifest, in that the Popes Liturgy from whence ours has been deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, is so. The Principal parts of the Mass-Book were borrowed from Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous <hi>Pagans;</hi> they came from <hi>Numa Pompilius:</hi> the Vestments, Holy water, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cense, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in the Roman Liturgy, were taken up from the Heathen; the Bishops of <hi>Rome</hi> thinking thereby to gain <hi>Pagans</hi> to the Christian Religion, just as the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops of <hi>England</hi> thought to gain Papists to the Protestant Religion, by the use of their Ceremonies.</p>
                  <p>What vain Repetitions does the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Prayer Book abound with?</p>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:110137:7"/>
                  <p> In one Service the Worshippers must repeat these words, <hi>Good Lord deliver us,</hi> eight times over, and <hi>We beseech thee to hear us,</hi> twenty times over. The <hi>Gloria Patri</hi> is to be repeated ten times in the same Morning or Evening Service.</p>
                  <p>That the Heathens were wont to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship their Idols just after the same man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, is clear from those words, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. <hi>When ye pray use not vain Repetitions,</hi> as the Heathens do, <hi>for they think that they shall be heard for their much speaking.</hi> When the same words are repeated often over like <hi>Battus</hi> his <hi>Montibus erant &amp; erant in montibus illis,</hi> it is vain Repetitions, such Battology is in the old Hymns of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then <hi>Greeks.</hi> And <hi>Beza</hi> notes that the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Liturgy does abound with them, wherein men are taught to cry <hi>Jesu, Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>su, miserere mei,</hi> no less than ten times one after another.</p>
                  <p>Some of the most learned Patrons of Liturgies produce it as an Argument for them, that the Heathen made use of Forms in their Idolatrous Worship. So, <hi>Jos. Vicecomes, de Missa Lib.</hi> 7. <hi>cap.</hi> 21. and from him <hi>Casaubon:</hi> And when <hi>Tertullian</hi> does declare that the Primitive Christians did pray <hi>Sine Monitore,</hi> judicious Authors do
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:110137:8"/> conceive, that his meaning is, that they did not as the Heathen were wont to do, <hi>Say their Prayers</hi> by the help of Forms which others had devised for them, but we are sure that God hath strictly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited his People all Symbolizing with the Heathen. He did forbid the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Israel</hi> some Civil usages, because he would not have them imitate the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then. Hence they might not wear a garment of Linnen and Woollen, <hi>Lev.</hi> 19. 19. the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Priests did wear such, and the Lords Servants must not follow their Example. <hi>Aquinas, Lyranus, Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>status,</hi> and some other Pontificians, as well as Protestant Writers take this to be the true Reason of that Prohibition.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Herodotus</hi> tells us, that the <hi>Arabians</hi> were wont to shave their hair, and to cut the corners of their Beards. They also, and the <hi>Syrians</hi> and <hi>Egyptians</hi> made baldness betwixt their eyes; therefore the Children of <hi>Israel</hi> might not do so, <hi>Lev.</hi> 19. 27. <hi>Deut.</hi> 14. 1. They might not sow their ground with divers sorts of seed, nor seeth a Kid in the Mothers milk, because the Heathen did so: But especially they might not imitate them in matters referring to the Worship of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:110137:8"/> God. Hence they were prohibited go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up by steps to the Altar, or to make any Altars of hewn Stone, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. 24, 26. The Heathen who fancied an <hi>august pompous worship,</hi> had such Altars as these prohibited ones, where they had Groves near their Altars: Therefore the Lords People might not plant a Grove near his Altar, <hi>Deut.</hi> 16. 21. They worshipped with their face towards the East, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Jews</hi> might not do so. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 8. 16.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="reason">
                  <p>Reason 2. <hi>From the matter of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Prayer Book.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There are many things contained there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in which cannot be justified under this Head. It is easie to produce and insist upon many Particulars, which might be improved as so many Arguments, evin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing that the <hi>English</hi> Liturgy is a Book unsuitable, and so unlawful to be made use of in the Worship of GOD.</p>
                  <p>For,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Some things appointed therein are now in the Judgment of Sober and Judicious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons extreamly ridiculous.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>How many odd and senceless Transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:110137:9"/> of the holy Scripture have been found therein?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Rom</hi> 12. 2. is translated thus, <hi>Be chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in your Shape,</hi> John 2. 10. Thus, <hi>when men be drunk.</hi> Luke 1. 36. Thus, <hi>This is the sixth Month which is called Barren:</hi> And Gal. 4. 25. <hi>That Ager in Arabia bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dereth on Jerusalem;</hi> with many more the like Absurdities.</p>
                  <p>But these things are so gross, that the Bishops in their Debate with Dr. <hi>Tuckney,</hi> Dr. <hi>Manton,</hi> &amp;c. have yielded to have them altered; so that the next Edition of the Common-Prayer Book is like to be Reformed. Nevertheless, they will not consent to have the corrupt Transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Psalter</hi> corrected: Still those words in <hi>Psal.</hi> 18. 9. are read, <hi>Or ever their Pots be made hot with Thorns, so let Indignation vex them, as a thing that is raw.</hi> What Nonsence is this!</p>
                  <p>And in the Liturgy, the writings of the Prophets, and the <hi>Acts</hi> of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles; yea, and the Book of the <hi>Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> are called <hi>Epistles.</hi> Moreover, those broken Responds, and <hi>Shreds of Prayer,</hi> as Mr. <hi>Cartwright</hi> calls them, which the Priests and People toss between them like Tennis-Balls, seem extreamly ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:110137:9"/> to standers by: Therefore such things ought not to be in the solemn Worship of God, who will not hold them guiltless that take his Name in vain.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>The Common-Prayer Book is guilty of violating the Sacred Word of God.</hi> Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the words of Scripture are thereby obliterated, and others put in their room: <hi>e. g.</hi> In the Catechism the Authors have changed those words in the fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment, <hi>The Lord blessed the Sabbath day,</hi> into <hi>the Lord blessed the Seventh day.</hi> Sometimes the Liturgy makes bold di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly and in terms to contradict the Scripture: For whereas in <hi>Psal.</hi> 105. 28. it is said, <hi>They were not rebellious against his Word,</hi> the Common-Prayer Book saith, <hi>They were not obedient to his word,</hi> which is directly contradictory to the Truth. Dr. <hi>Spark,</hi> (notwithstanding his affection for the Liturgy) told the then <hi>Archbishop of Canterbury,</hi> that so to read the words, is to charge <hi>Moses</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> with falshood. The Liturgy saith, That the Rod of the Wicked shall not <hi>come</hi> into the lot of the Righteous, whenas <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> only saith, that it shall not <hi>rest</hi> there: and sometimes the Common-Prayer Book adds to the Scripture; there are three
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:110137:10"/> whole Verses added to the fourteenth Psalm; And the <hi>Gloria Patri</hi> is frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly added to Scriptures, as if it were Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonical: Sometimes words are sacrilegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously stollen out of the Bible. <hi>e. g.</hi> In the Seventy second Psalm, the last verse is omitted: so is the Scriptural Titles of many Psalms; and I know not how of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten those words, <hi>Praise ye the Lord,</hi> are left out. Amongst men Clipping and corrupting of Coyn is Treason: And cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly it is a dreadful thing to addd to, or take from the Word of God. <hi>Deut.</hi> 4. 2. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22. 19.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. In the Liturgy <hi>The Apochrypha books are made equal with, nay, advanced above the Holy Scripture.</hi> In the Preface to the Common-Prayer Book, it is said, <hi>That nothing is ordained to be read but the pure Word of God, or that which is evidently grounded on the same.</hi> But is the Apochrypha so? Indeed the Liturgy appoints them to be read as Lessons, just as I find it in the Popes Service-book, and in a greater pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion than Scripture; for (as some have observed) of an hundred Seventy two Apochryphal Chapters, but Thirty eight are omitted: So that these Books are equallized with the pure Word of God.</p>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:110137:10"/>
                  <p> In the <hi>Conference</hi> at <hi>Hampton</hi> Court, the Bishop of <hi>Winchester</hi> spoke out plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and said those Books must needs be held <hi>canonici ad informandos mores.</hi> Nay, the Liturgy advanceth them above the Scripture, by intimating that they are <hi>more Edifying,</hi> and can be less spared than many Portions of the Holy Canon; and by ordering them to be read on the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est Holy-days, and many of them twice, some thrice in one Year: And that which adds to this Iniquity, is, That the Lies, and Magical Prescriptions, and most corrupt Doctrine expressed in the Book of <hi>Tobit,</hi> have been appointed to be read, as if these things were Divine.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>Such things are enjoyned in the Common-Prayer Book, as (to my Conscience) can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be practised without Sin.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To Instance, Ministers are required to give the Holy Communion to all new Married Persons; whenas Marriage Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stivals use to be accompanyed with such Divertisements and Merriments, as make Persons altogether unfit for a Present actual Participation at the Holy Table.</p>
                  <p>Why then does the Common-Prayer Book appoint the Minister to give them the Sacrament on that very day?</p>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:110137:11"/>
                  <p> By that Doctrine, all that may marry may come to the Lords Supper, whenas Marriage is an Ordinance, which Men as Men (and not as Christians only) have a right unto: So that by this Prescription many will be put upon making them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves guilty of the Body and Blood of the Lord, and eat and drink damnation to their own Souls. And this does the Common-Prayer Book compell them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; notwithstanding in the <hi>Articles of the Church of England,</hi> it is expresly and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodoxly declared, that <hi>unworthy Receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers purchase to themselves damnation.</hi> Artic. 23. <hi>&amp;</hi> 29.</p>
                  <p>Again, when any man is buried, the Priest must say at his Grave, <hi>Almighty God has taken to himself the Soul of this dear Brother;</hi> perhaps the most wicked wretch on the Earth, and that <hi>his Body is commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the ground, in sure and certain hope of a Resurrection to everlasting Life:</hi> Though he did never truly, nor so much as visi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to the judgment of Rational Charity, repent of his Sins.</p>
                  <p>What Minister can do this with a good Conscience?</p>
                  <p>And there are many Superstitions both recommended and imposed in the Liturgy.</p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:110137:11"/>
                  <p> The putting on of the Ring in Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, especially the making of that Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony to be an Essential matter, is Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stition: And I do not see how Common-Prayer-Worshippers can clear themseives from all Superstition, when they use those words in the <hi>Canticle Benedicite;</hi> saying, <hi>O Ananias; O Azarias, and Misael, bless the Lord.</hi> And when the Priest is appointed to <hi>Church</hi> Women, and that they must at that time <hi>offer their Accustomed Offerings,</hi> it is Jewish Superstition. And the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation of <hi>Popish</hi> Holy-days, especially such as are dedicated to Saints, I look upon as highly superstitious: The like I believe concerning wearing of a <hi>Surplice,</hi> as a signification of Purity; when holy Vest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments were in use amongst the <hi>Jews,</hi> they had an Express Commandment from God about them. Should they have made a <hi>Mitre</hi> or an <hi>Ephod,</hi> or any other Ecclesi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>astical Garments of their own heads, they would have sinned greatly; witness <hi>Judg.</hi> 8. 27. If the Church of old had no power to appoint sacred Vestments, no more has the Church in these days. It is incumbent on them who affirm they have such power, to produce their Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which they can ever do. Moreover,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:110137:12"/> the <hi>Surplice</hi> is immediately borrowed from Idolatrous Mass-Mongers. In the <hi>Roman Liturgy</hi> it is ordained that the Priest shall say Service in his <hi>Surplice,</hi> and has no power to sanctifie Bells, or Water, or any thing else, except his <hi>Surplice</hi> be on; which made <hi>Latimer</hi> when the <hi>Surplice</hi> was pluckt from him in his Degradation, in an holy scorn to say, <hi>Now I can make no more Holy Water.</hi> Neither can any Priest make his <hi>Breaden God</hi> except he have it on; see <hi>Rhem. Annot.</hi> on 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 29.</p>
                  <p>Shall Protestants do thus?</p>
                  <p>Dr. <hi>Abbot</hi> (who was no Fanatick) in his Book of Antichrist, <hi>Ch.</hi> 11. <hi>Sect.</hi> 26. saith, <hi>That all Priestly Garments, whereby Ministers are distinguished from the rest of the Church, are a special part of the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of the Beast.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And who did the Papists take the <hi>Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plice</hi> from?</p>
                  <p>Partly from the <hi>Jews</hi> indeed, but also from the Heathen of old: There were <hi>Vestments for the Worshippers of</hi> Baal, 2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 10. 22. Bishop <hi>Jewel</hi> (that great Light in the <hi>English</hi> Church) in the Defence of his Apology, <hi>p.</hi> 346. quotes and approves these Words out of <hi>Nicholaus Leonicenus,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:110137:12"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Priests of</hi> Isis <hi>used to wear Linnen Surplices, which seems to be derived from them to our time.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For they that amongst us serve the Holy Altars, may not suffer the hair of their heads, or their beards to grow, and in their Divine Service they use Linnen Garments:</hi> Thus he.</p>
                  <p>Moreover, the greatest of our Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant Divines have disliked this Supersti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Garment.</p>
                  <p>So <hi>Martyr, Brentius, Bullinger, Gualter, Beza, Zanchy, Hemmingius, Polanus;</hi> and many others.</p>
                  <p>To say no more of this, Mr. <hi>Nichols</hi> his Argument, which he proposed to the Bishop of <hi>Chester,</hi> is not easie to be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered; it was this, All Vestments ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriated to the Worship of God, and appointed for the signification of Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Duties by the Will of Man, are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful, but the Surplice is so, <hi>Ergo.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And the <hi>Sign of the Cross</hi> in Baptism is as bad as this: That I confess was an old Superstion, it crept early into the Church; but the first Users of it (so far as I am able to learn) were bad Men, and gross Hereticks, <hi>viz. Valentin</hi> and <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanus.</hi> Mr. <hi>Robert Parker</hi> in his Elaborate Discourse about the Cross, proveth, that
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:110137:13"/> it is a Sin against all the Ten Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and a breach of the very Letter of the Second Commandment. For Men to appoint a Religious Ceremony, is a direct violation of the Second Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which forbids all humane Inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in Divine Worship, as any part there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: And the Arguments which are brought against the Use of <hi>Oyl, Cream, Salt, Spit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle</hi> in Baptism, (practised by the Papists) hold as well against the Cross. The Priest may as well take a Thorn, and prick the Child's Forehead with it, to put in mind that Christ was crowned with Thorns, and that Christians must suffer, as to Cross him with any such signification.</p>
                  <p>Hereby too great a respect is put up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that which was the Cursed Instrument of Christ's Death. Suppose a Man should honour one of the Nails which fastned Christ to the Cross, (as some Fable that <hi>Constantine</hi> did) or the Spear that pierced Him, or the Whip wherewith <hi>Pilate</hi> caus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Him to be Scourged, would it not be horrid Superstition? Judicious and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Men have argued thus, if a Child should Worship the Gallows on which his Father was hanged, that would manifest him to be ungracious and unnatural; and the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:110137:13"/> in adoring the Cross do as bad. It's true, that the Scripture speaks honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of the Cross of Christ, whereby we are crucified to the World, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. 14. But that is not to be understood of the Cross of Wood, nor yet of an Airy or Watery Cross, but of the Death of that Jesus who suffered on the Cross. In a word, Mr. <hi>Parker</hi> sheweth, <hi>That the Cross is the greatest Devil amongst all the Idols of</hi> Rome. This Superstition hath been te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stified against by <hi>Zegedinus, Zepperus, Gou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lartius, Bucanus,</hi> Dr. <hi>Fulk,</hi> Dr. <hi>Rainolds,</hi> and innumerable other Learned Protestant Writers: Nay, some Praelatical Men, who could comply with all the other Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, have scrupled this of the Cross in Baptism. Dr. <hi>Tailor</hi> Confesseth, that they have in respect of the Cross retain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed an uninstituted Ceremony as a part of External Worship.</p>
                  <p>I shall here take Notice of but one Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perstition more, enjoyned by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Prayer-Book, <hi>viz.</hi> That of <hi>Kneeling at the Sacrament.</hi> Men pretend that they Kneel out of Reverence to Christ, but Christ himself was personally present, when his Disciples did partake of the Lord's Supper, yet they did not kneel,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:110137:14"/> but used the Table gesture then customa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry amongst the <hi>Jews.</hi> Good and wise Men have chosen great Sufferings rather than to comply with this Invention.</p>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> (see his Answer to <hi>Bailie,</hi> p. 19.) was proffered not only the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of his Ministry, but great Prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, on Condition he would but <hi>for one time Kneel in the Act of receiving the sacramental Bread and Wine:</hi> But he Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected this Argument, <hi>Non-instituted Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship is unacceptable to God: Kneeling in the Act of receiving is Non-instituted. Worship,</hi> Ergo, <hi>It is unacceptable to God.</hi> So did that Holy and Learned Man choose ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to lose his Preferments and his Livelyhood too, than to be guilty of such a Superstition.</p>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Dyton</hi> and Mr. <hi>Ware,</hi> (worthy Men both of them) dyed in Prison, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they durst not Kneel at the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                  <p>It is certain, that in the Primitive Times Christians did not Kneel in the Participation of the Eucharist. In the <hi>Nicene Council,</hi> An. 325. there was a <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree against Kneeling in the Church on the Lord's-day:</hi> So that either there was no Sacrament administred on the Lords-Day,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:110137:14"/> (which to suppose is irrational) or there was no kneeling at it.</p>
                  <p>This is also to be seen in the <hi>sixth Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil</hi> held at <hi>Constantinople.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Kneeling was first enjoyned (so far as I can understand) in the year 1226, by Pope <hi>Honorius,</hi> being fitted to the Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry of Transubstantiation. Some Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish Writers confess, that if the substance of the Bread remain after the Consecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; they by kneeling before the Bread should be guilty of as vile Idolatry, as ever the <hi>Egpptians</hi> were guilty of when they worshiped every kind of Creature.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Costerus</hi> (the Jesuit) professeth that he would be torn in pieces by wild Horses, rather then he would kneel at the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, did he not believe the bodily Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence.</p>
                  <p>So that Kneelers do dangerously sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolize with the Papists in their worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of their breaden god.</p>
                  <p>That Religious worship which is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a Creature, and with respect to it, having no allowance from God, is against the Commandment: but so is Kneeling before the Bread and Wine.</p>
                  <p>These things then prove that the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glish Liturgy is very corrupt. Now <hi>to</hi>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:110137:15"/>
                     <hi>offer to the Lord a corrupt thing, or that which is Lame and Sick, is evil,</hi> Mal. 1. 13, 14.</p>
                  <p>It is in vain for men to please them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, that though they joyn in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Prayer-Worship, they do not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove thereof.</p>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> in his Book against set Forms of Prayer, does truly and judiciously ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve, that <hi>Paul</hi> in practising a few Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies out of the Book of the Law, did thereby declare his subjection to the whole order of Worship, prescribed by the Authority of that Law; <hi>Acts</hi> 21. 24. 26. in doing of which, undoubtedly he had sinned, if God had not warranted the continuance of that Worship for a Season.</p>
                  <p>Thus he that shall joyn with a few Prayers in the Common-Prayer Book, does really profess his subjection to the whole order of Worship prescribed in that Book.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="reason">
                  <p>Reason 3. <hi>Because publick Liturgies of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane composure, are an Innovation and Devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation from primitive purity.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Common-Prayer Worshippers are wont to urge and argue from <hi>the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity of Liturgies,</hi> but I turn that wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:110137:15"/> against them. Let not any quibble with the Notation of the word <hi>Liturgy,</hi> which is as much as to say, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Opus publicum,</hi> or of the word <hi>Litany,</hi> which cometh from the Greek, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Precor;</hi> under these notions and accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the words, who ever denyed that the Church of God has always had a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy, <hi>h. e.</hi> a Service of his own Institu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? but set Forms of Prayer devised by Men are an Innovation. Had a Liturgy been needful for the Edification of the Church, undoubtedly the Lord Christ, or the Apostles by His direction, would have composed one, which none of them ever did.</p>
                  <p>And therefore those Men who take up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them to compose and impose a Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy on the Churches, assume to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves more than Apostolical Power.</p>
                  <p>I am surpized with wonderment, that in the late <hi>grand Debate, p.</hi> 110. between twelve Bishops and others, with some learned men amongst the <hi>Nonconformists,</hi> these words are found as proceeding from our Prelates, <hi>That there were ancient Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies in the Church, is evident.</hi> St. <hi>Chryso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stom,</hi> St. <hi>Basil, and others, and the Greek tell us of</hi> St. <hi>James his, elder than they.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:110137:16"/>
                  <p> This very Passage alone, is enough to convince me, that the Bishops have a desperate cause. I marvel not that Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificians, such as <hi>Xaintesius, Possevinus, Lindanus,</hi> and others, professed Papists, speak after this rate; and yet the more ingenious amongst them confess the Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies mentioned to be spurious.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Durandus</hi> in his <hi>Rationale,</hi> lib. 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. honestly confesseth the Truth: That in the Primitive Times there was no Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy used in the Church.</p>
                  <p>As for those fathered on the Apostles, and the Ancient Writers (called Fathers) after their days, many Learned men, but especially <hi>Peter Martyr, Morney, Rivet, Cocus, Rainold, Voetius,</hi> &amp;c. have by irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fragable Arguments, evinced them to be Supposititious and Spurious things. In that said to be <hi>Chrysostoms,</hi> the Church is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to pray for Pope <hi>Nicholas,</hi> who li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved not till five hundred years after <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sostom</hi> was dead: As for St. <hi>James</hi>'s Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, it is so unlike an Apostle, as that <hi>Bellarmin</hi> himself judgeth it to be either wholly Spurious, or that others have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to it what they pleased; it mentions the <hi>Anchorets,</hi> and has other words in it, not known in the Apostles days.</p>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:110137:16"/>
                  <p> Of the like Authority are the Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies Fathered on <hi>Peter, Mark,</hi> and <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew,</hi> in which there are Prayers for <hi>Popes, Patriarchs,</hi> and <hi>Archbishops,</hi> Creatures not known in the World, till long after the Apostles were dead.</p>
                  <p>It is clear from the words of <hi>Justin Martyr,</hi> (in <hi>Orat. Apol.)</hi> who lived 160 years after Christ, that then there was no Book of Prayer used by Christians; for he saith, That the Minister did <hi>pour out his Prayers,</hi>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as strength and utterance was afforded to him from Heaven:</hi> It is as clear that in <hi>Tertullians</hi> time, (who lived 200 years after Christ) there was no Church-Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy; for he <hi>(Apol. Cap.</hi> 2.) declares, that Christians in those days prayed <hi>Sine Monitore quia de pectore,</hi> without the help of a prompted Form, because from their Hearts.</p>
                  <p>And that there was no Liturgy in some Churches, or of general use in the Church for above four hundred years, is manifest from the words of <hi>Socrates,</hi> (who lived <hi>Anno</hi> 430.) he saith, There were scarce two Christians found, who used the same words in Prayer. <hi>Hist.</hi> l. 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 21. It is true, that about the year 350. <hi>(plus</hi>
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:110137:17"/>
                     <hi>minus,)</hi> some Churches in <hi>Africa</hi> begun to use stinted Liturgies, which was oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casioned by the gross Ignorance and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terodoxy that many of the Clergy were then found guilty of: So that the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Carthage,</hi> Anno 395. ordered that Ministers should not use Prayers compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed by themselves, <hi>without consulting their more able Brethren.</hi> Hence also came in <hi>Homilies,</hi> because many Ministers were as unable to preach, as they were unfit to pray. In the declining Ages of the Church, many Liturgical Books were composed, <hi>Sed ab initio non fuit sic:</hi> There are the Prayer Books of <hi>Isidorus, Flaccus, Strabo, Maurus, Berno, Hildebertus,</hi> and others; as whoso pleaseth to consult <hi>Cassanders Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgica,</hi> will see, these things if searched into will be found the Truth. There are who plead, that in the Jewish Church of old, there were Forms Prayer used besides those which were of Divine Inspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
                  <q>Credat Judaeus Apella.</q>
                  <p>I know that some Jewish Doctors tell us, That <hi>Ezra</hi> and the <hi>Men of the great Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue,</hi>
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:110137:17"/> appointed eighteen Benedictions, yea, and that <hi>David</hi> appointed an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Benedictions. <hi>Vide Buxtorf. Synagog. Cap.</hi> 5. <hi>In fine Drusii Praeterit. ad Acts</hi> 3. &amp; 10. <hi>Schindler Pentaglot. in voce Manach.</hi> And I have seen Liturgies written in the Hebrew Tongue, but it is easie to perceive that they are late Composures. They that think to find any such compiled before the Church of the Jews was degenerat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into its present woful estate, will find themselves disappointed, as Bishop <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drews</hi> was, when he caused a Jewish Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy to be translated out of the Hebrew into the Latin Tongue, hoping that he should have found something therein to countenance the English Liturgy. <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brard</hi> has emitted a Jewish Common-Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Book, wherein are Prayers for the Dead, a Superstitious Commemoration of Saints: of so little weight is the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument taken from the <hi>Jews</hi> Liturgies.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="reason">
                  <p>Reason 4. <hi>In this Age of Light, it would in me, (and in all others so Educated and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structed as I have been) appear to be a great Apostacy, should I in the least countenance or comply with the Common-Prayer-Worship.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:110137:18"/>
                  <p> The Corruptions of the English Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy have been abundantly discovered and born witness against by many Learned and worthy Men, whom God has raised up and enabled to do that Service for his Name and Truth.</p>
                  <p>The Books of the Famous <hi>Cartwright</hi> were long since Published, and since that a Treatise called, <hi>A Survey of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Prayer,</hi> and <hi>the Exceptions of the Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don Ministers,</hi> which caused them to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuse Subscription to the Liturgy, and <hi>the Apology of the Non-conformists in Lincoln<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shire,</hi> and <hi>the Reasons of those in Cornwall, and Devon,</hi> and <hi>the Defence of those Reasons, in three parts;</hi> besides many other Tracts emitted very lately; by all which the Light is convincingly manifested before the World.</p>
                  <p>Yea, and there have been many, and those too, not of wilfull Tempers, but very humble and conscientious; nor of weak parts, but as Eminent for Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Judgment, as any in the World, who have chosen to suffer, rather than to sin in complying with the Liturgy. Amongst these, I might mention Dr. <hi>John Rainold,</hi> Dr. <hi>Ames,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Robert Parker,</hi> (a Man of vast Reading and Abilities,)
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:110137:18"/> Mr. <hi>Dod,</hi> (whom Mr. <hi>Burroughs</hi> has fitly sty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>Moses</hi> of his Time,) Mr. <hi>Bradshaw</hi> and Mr. <hi>Nichols,</hi> not to speak of others.</p>
                  <p>Only I would not forget those Eminent and Faithful Ministers of Christ, who were driven into an <hi>American Desart,</hi> the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Cause of whose Exile and Sufferings, was, because they durst not touch with the Common-Prayer Book; and since their being in <hi>New-England,</hi> some of them have by their Writings testified against it. The nine <hi>Positions</hi> (though written by Mr. <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venport,</hi> had the Approbation of the rest of the <hi>Elders in New-England,</hi> and therein Reasons are given, why it is unlawfull to be present at the Common Prayer-Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, or any part thereof.</p>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>John Cotton</hi> of <hi>Boston,</hi> (a Man deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedly Famous in both <hi>Englands)</hi> has done the like: And Mr. <hi>John Allen</hi> of <hi>Dedham</hi> in <hi>New-England,</hi> (Mr. <hi>Shepherd</hi> of <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge</hi> joyning with him) in his <hi>defence of the nine Positions,</hi> has expresly declared the Unlawfulness of being present at the Common-Prayer-Worship.</p>
                  <p>As for me, your self knoweth what my Education has been. My Father was on Holy and a Learned Man, and one that suffered much for his <hi>Non-conformity;</hi>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:110137:19"/> should I once go to hear Common-Prayer, I seriously profess, I know not how I should be able to look my Father in the Face in the other World; much less how I should answer Christ at the great Day for my Apostacy from those Principles of Truth which my Father has instruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me in, both by Word and Example; <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. 18. is of weight with me.</p>
                  <p>These, Sir, are some of the Reasons why I judge it would be sin in me to own the Common-Prayer-Worship: I have omitted the mentioning of many particulars con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Liturgy, which <hi>as to the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of them are false</hi> and corrupt. e. g. It is there affirmed, that <hi>Children Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed have all things necessary to Salvation, and are undoubtedly saved:</hi> Yea, that <hi>it is certain from Gods Word, that if a baptized Child dye before actual Sin, 'tis saved:</hi> this savours of <hi>Pelagianism:</hi> And that there are only two <hi>Sacraments necessary to Salvation,</hi> which implies a double Error, <hi>viz.</hi> that the Sacraments are necessary to Salvation; and that there are more Sacraments of the New Testament than two: And the Book saith that <hi>some sins are deadly,</hi> as if the Popish distinction of sins into <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal</hi> and <hi>Venial</hi> were a sound distinction,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:110137:19"/> and that Christ has Redeemed <hi>all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I might here also have added, that a <hi>stinted Liturgy is opposite to the Spirit of Prayer.</hi> The Scripture teacheth, That Christians should pray <hi>with all Prayer and Supplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the Spirit.</hi> Ephes. 6. 18. which they cannot do, if they tye themselves up to a set Form never to be varied from: I let pass that Argument, <hi>from the Mischief of a Prescript Liturgy;</hi> it is the Instrument of a foolish Shepherd: An Idol and a dumb Ministry is thereby continued in the Church.</p>
                  <p>It is well known, that in a place in <hi>Kent,</hi> a common Fidler read Service for 12 <hi>d. per</hi> week; and perhaps that was more than he deserved: But let me seri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously add this further, That a <hi>prescribed Book is an Image or Help to Prayer devised by Men, but not ordained by God,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore forbidden in the second Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> speaketh weightily, in say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>It is unlawful to bring in ordinarily any other Book into the publick Worship of God, beside the Book of God.</hi> To bring in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Book, is like bringing in of another Altar into the Temple besides the Lords
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:110137:20"/> Altar. If it be a sin to set up a Post by God's Post, and a Threshold by his Threshold, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 42. 8. then it is a sin to set up a Book by Gods Book; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequently it is a sin to joyn with, or to countenance them that do so.</p>
                  <p>But before I proceed to your next <hi>Question,</hi> give me leave to speak a few words in answer to that which some take to be a sufficient justification of the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy, or at leastwise of their partaking in that Worship, viz. <hi>In that the first Collectors and Publishers of it were good men, and divers of them died Martyrs.</hi> Answer. Are not good Men, especially in times of Darkness fallible, and their Example not to be followed, wherein they have fallen short of the Rule. In some Ages good Men may do that, which if their Successors having greater light should fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low them in, they would not be good; witness the <hi>Polygamy</hi> of the Fathers, not to mention other Errors: But as to the matter before us, thus it hath been. The whole Liturgy was said or sung in Latin in the Reign of King <hi>Henry</hi> 8. untill the year 1545, and then the Litany and no other part of the Liturgy was permitted in English; and that was the furthest
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:110137:20"/> pace the Reformation stept in that Kings Reign. See <hi>Fuller Church-History.</hi> Book 7. <hi>p.</hi> 386. In <hi>Anno</hi> 1548. came forth the first Edition of the Common-Prayer Book in King <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth's time.</p>
                  <p>There is no rule of Charity that does require us to believe that all the Persons employed thereabout were good Men: For one of them was <hi>George Day</hi> the <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop of Chichester,</hi> he was a dissembling Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite, pretending to be a Protestant, but afterwards shew'd himself to be a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pist: Yet many set awork about that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair, were truly Pious Men, who acted faithfully, according to the Light they had received in those dawnings of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation out of Popish Darkness in <hi>England.</hi> Bishop <hi>Ridley</hi> had an hand in that first English Liturgy, being the <hi>hottest Stickler for Conformity in those days,</hi> but GOD gave him to see his Error before his Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdom, as is clear from his Letter to Mr. <hi>Hooper,</hi> published by Mr. <hi>Fox.</hi> Vol. 3. <hi>p.</hi> 146, 147.</p>
                  <p>Archbishop <hi>Cranmer</hi> was another, and the most Eminent amongst the Compi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of the English Liturgy: But it is related in the <hi>History of the Troubles at Franckford,</hi> p. 42. <hi>That</hi> Cranmer <hi>had drawn</hi>
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:110137:21"/>
                     <hi>up a Book of Prayers far more perfect than that which now we have, and that it could not take place, because he was Matched with, and overpowred by a Popish and a Wicked Clergy.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>So that the Common Prayer Book came forth no better than now we see it. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheless, Eminent Divines did then te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stifie against those Remainders of Popery which it does abound with.</p>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Rogers</hi> (the Protomartyr in Queen <hi>Mary's</hi> Reign) and Mr. <hi>Hooper,</hi> (who dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Martyr also) were much troubled at the Service-Book. Moreover, great and learned Men of other Nations found fault with it; so did <hi>Calvin,</hi> and <hi>Bucer,</hi> and at last <hi>Peter Martyr:</hi> And <hi>Bullinger</hi> declared that he should be loth to make use of it in his Church. Likewise <hi>John â Lasco</hi> (that famous and noble Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er) expressed great dissatisfaction at the <hi>English Liturgy.</hi> That Mr. <hi>Knox</hi> and the Chief Reformers in <hi>Scotland</hi> were offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at it, every Body knoweth.</p>
                  <p>In Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Reign, the Bishops made the Common Prayer Book to be in several things worse and more intolerable than it was in the Dayes of King <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward:</hi> For in his time it was left free
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:110137:21"/> what to be read, nor were some Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitious Ceremonies then Imposed upon the Consciences of such as could not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with them.</p>
                  <p>No less than Twenty six Lessons of Canonical Scripture, appointed to be read in King <hi>Edward</hi>'s Kalender, are Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilegiously blotted out of the latter Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer Book. Also the Bishops have Expunged a Prayer against the <hi>Pope of</hi> Rome <hi>and his detestable Enormities,</hi> which was in King <hi>Edward</hi>'s Book; and that <hi>Express Declaration against the Corporeal Presence</hi> is in the Liturgy Published <hi>Anno</hi> 1559. left out, in Compliance with the Papists.</p>
                  <p>This was the very Reason why the Clergy-men were so inflexible in their adherence to the Liturgy, and the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship prescribed thereby; it was because they resolved to go no farther from <hi>Rome</hi> than needs they must, and from a vain Perswasion that they should thereby gain Papists over to their Communion.</p>
                  <p>But <hi>the Learned Primate of Ireland</hi> does observe, and ingeniously acknowledge, that Experience has manifested that the Papists are not won, but rather hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in their Superstitions, by such Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods.</p>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:110137:22"/>
                  <p> It may be time will discover, that some who pretend Zeal for the Common-Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Book, are carrying on a design for <hi>Rome:</hi> The Liturgy came from thence, and will perhaps lead thither again.</p>
                  <p>The Riddle of the Snow and the Water may be applyed here,</p>
                  <q>Mater me genuit, Mater quoque gignitur ex me.</q>
                  <p>Not but that some who Comply with the Service-Book are true Protestants, and would suffer with their Non-conforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Brethren (who cannot go so far as they) rather than Embrace Popery.</p>
                  <p>Nevertheless, the Liturgy has in it self a tendency that way, and will by such as are not hearty Protestants be Improved accordingly.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="question">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:110137:22"/>
               <p> I Proceed now to the Second Enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>VIZ.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVhat Reason have you to Scruple the Lawfulness of laying the Hand on the BIBLE, and Kissing the Book in Sivearing?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I Answer briefly.</p>
               <div n="1" type="reason">
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>We do not find in the Scripture that the Lord's Servants were wont to Swear af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that Manner.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There we read of Lifting up the Hand in Swearing, which is like lifting up the Hands or Eyes in Prayer, a natural sign of Worship. To <hi>lift up the Hand to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven is a proverbial Expression of a solemn Oath,</hi> Gen. 14. 22. Ezek. 20. 23. Rev. 10. 5. In many Nations they used this gesture. The Judges in <hi>France</hi> say to Him that is to Swear, <hi>Lift up your Hand,</hi>
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:110137:23"/> except it be an Ecclesiastick Person, and they bid him put his hand to his Breast. The <hi>Romans</hi> of old, so the <hi>Italians</hi> and <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards,</hi> have used to lift up the Finger when they Swear solemnly.</p>
                  <p>I cannot justifie the practice of the <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> who in taking an Oath, <hi>lift up three Fingers,</hi> as thereby intimating, that they invoke the Sacred Trinity.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="reason">
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Laying the hand on the Book is a sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolizing with Popish Idolaters, and Superstiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Jews.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This Ceremony is immediately derived from the Papists, who are wont as they lay the hand on the Book in Swearing, to say, <hi>So help me God and these holy Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lists,</hi> which is gross Idolatry; and it is not much better when it is said, <hi>So help you the Contents of this Book.</hi> The judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Rivet,</hi> in <hi>Psal.</hi> 24. p. 308, 309. wish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that custom of <hi>touching the Book,</hi> were not at all used: He saith, The abuse of it by Idolaters, makes it to be a Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony not fit to be retained as an indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent thing: See him also in <hi>Gen.</hi> 24. <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercit.</hi> 110. <hi>p.</hi> 541.</p>
                  <p>Some have observed, that the <hi>Jews</hi> when an Oath was to be Administred, did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:110137:23"/> either the Book of the <hi>Law,</hi> or of the <hi>Psalms,</hi> or some other sacred thing.</p>
                  <p>And that Superstition of theirs has given occasion to the Papists to bring either the Holy Evangelists, or else some <hi>Sacred Relique,</hi> and set it before him that is to swear, thereby to stir up his dull mind to the more Reverence and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Pareus</hi> saith expresly, That it is <hi>Popish Superstition, for men in taking an Oath to touch the Gospel with their fingers.</hi> Comment. in <hi>Gen.</hi> 24. 2.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="reason">
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Kissing in a Religious way is a gesture of Adoration.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>When 'tis said, <hi>Psalm</hi> 2. 12. <hi>Kiss the Son,</hi> the meaning is, <hi>Worship Him: Job</hi> saith, he did not when he beheld the Sun and the Moon <hi>Kiss</hi> his hand, <hi>Chap.</hi> 31. <hi>Verse</hi> 26, 27. because Idolaters not being able to reach the Sun, in token of Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration were wont to Kiss their hands, as many Learned men have out of <hi>Tertullian, Pliny</hi> and others truly noted. The Worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of the Calves at <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel</hi> kis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed them, 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 19. 18. <hi>Hos.</hi> 12. 2. And so did the Heathen Idolaters, <hi>kiss their Images,</hi> a sign of Worship. <hi>Minutus</hi>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:110137:24"/>
                     <hi>Felix</hi> Reports, That <hi>Caecilius</hi> kissed the Image of <hi>Serapis,</hi> thereby testifying his Veneration and Adoration of that false God: <hi>Cicero</hi> tells us, that the worshippers of <hi>Hercules,</hi> had by their frequent <hi>kissing</hi> of his Statue, caused it to be much worn.</p>
                  <p>And from the Heathen have the Papists learned to <hi>Kiss their Images,</hi> yea and to <hi>Kiss the Book too.</hi> For the Priest in Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brating the Mass, is not onely to Kiss the Altar nine times, but he must also take the <hi>Book of the Gospel and Kiss it.</hi> This is Clearly to worship a Book; and so to give unto a Creature that Honour which is due to God alone.</p>
                  <p>The most Learned <hi>Voetius,</hi> in his Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, <hi>de Superstitione,</hi> p. 156. writeth against this practice: And whereas some have objected, that Dr. <hi>Ames</hi> in his Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, and in his fresh Suit against Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, has pleaded for this Ceremony; <hi>Voe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> saith, that what <hi>Ames</hi> speaks, is ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther an Excuse than an Approbation of that Practice.</p>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Burroughs</hi> on <hi>Hosea</hi> 13. 2. observes, that it is false Worship, to give Religious Respect to any Creature, whatever the Creature be, by kissing as well as by bowing to it: And (saith he,) <hi>I know no</hi>
                     <pb n="43" facs="tcp:110137:24"/>
                     <hi>reason why a Book may not be set up to bow to, as well as to be kissed in taking an Oath.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That Searching and Acute Divine, Dr. <hi>Thomas Goodwin,</hi> has sometimes professed, that of all the Ceremonies, he looked up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that of Kissing the Book in Swearing to be the most Idolatrous and Abominable, and that he often wondred that it had been no more witnessed against.</p>
                  <p>And now Sir, you have my Thoughts concerning both your Questions; and you see the grounds I go upon: If you judge that any of your Friends will receive Light and Confirmation in the Truth thereby; you may privately Communicate what I have written to you, only let my Name (which can add no Authority to the Truth) be concealed: So I commend you to the Grace of Christ, praying that his Holy Spirit may lead us into all Truth.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>